{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "People affected by this phenomenon founded the Last Man Club, and one attempt to fix it was the Shelterbelt Project. This disaster was named in the aftermath of Black Sunday and was preceded by the “great plow-up.” Many individuals affected by this period’s “black blizzards” migrated along Route 66 to California’s Central Valley, where they were branded as “Okies”. For ten points, name this ecological disaster during the Great Depression in which drought caused storms of topsoil across the southern Great Plains.",
      "answer": "Dust Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "Carl Peters’ attempt to implement cotton quotas in this modern day country led to the Maji Maji Rebellion. The Chama Cha Mapinduzi party holds power in this country and was once led by a man who promoted “ujaama” with the Arusha Declaration. The annexation of this country’s Kagera province led this country to defeat and depose Idi Amin in neighboring Uganda. Julius Nyerere once led, for ten points, what African country formed in 1964 from the merger of Tanganyika and Zanzibar?",
      "answer": "Tanzania"
    },
    {
      "question": "During one of these events, a Cheyenne tribe killed a white buffalo and inscribed a peace treaty on its skin. A Roman tradition during one of these events involved a procession honoring the fertility god Priapus; that event is also known as the “Tears of Saint Lawrence.” Giovanni Schiaparelli proved that one of these events is caused by a trail of debris from the Tempel-Tuttle comet entering Earth’s atmosphere. The Perseids and Leonids are examples of, for ten points, what astronomical events in which streaks of light cross the sky?",
      "answer": [
        "meteor showers",
        "Leonids and/or Perseids before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A popular myth about these people was promulgated by the Geatish Society during the early 19th century. Charles the Simple bought off these people with the Treaty of Saint-Clair-sur-Epte. These people were responsible for the destruction and looting of the Lindisfarne abbey in 793, and they raided much of Northern and Western Europe by traveling in longships. For ten points, name these Germanic people, whose rulers included Canute the Great, who were notorious for their pillaging.",
      "answer": "Vikings"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s 1974 Eurovision entry, “And After the Farewell,” was used by the MFA to signal the start of a revolution against Marcello Caetano. In that revolution, flowers were placed in gun barrels, as only four citizens of this country were killed as Antonio Salazar’s Estado Novo was overthrown. For ten points, name this country, which granted independence to Angola and Mozambique in 1975, a year after the Carnation Revolution peacefully brought a military junta to power in Lisbon.",
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Neutral White Cross was established to provide medical relief during this period. The U.S. intervened to stop the German ship Ypiranga from arming militants in this conflict. Venustiano Carranza held the Convention of Aguascalientes during this period, which was ushered in by the Plan of San Luis Potosi. The Ten Tragic Days, which resulted in the assassination of Francisco Madero, took place during, for ten points, what decade-long revolution that began with the ousting of Porfirio Diaz and whose military actions ended with the pacification of Pancho Villa?",
      "answer": "Mexican Revolution"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Ogle supported this man’s candidacy with the Gold Spoon Oration, though his detractors called him “granny.” A newspaper editorial critical of this man inspired his supporters’ “log cabin and hard cider” campaign. His 1811 victory over a group of Shawnee Indians led to his party’s adoption of the slogan “Tippecanoe and Tyler Too”. For ten points, what Whig defeated Martin van Buren in the 1840 election but died of pneumonia a month after his inauguration?",
      "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the cantata Gloria e Imeneo for Louis XV’s wedding and celebrated the defense of Corfu with the oratorio Juditha triumphans. Violas depict a barking sheepdog in one of his concertos, which was originally published with explanatory sonnets in The Contest Between Harmony and Invention. This violinst composed many of his works for a girl’s orphanage in Venice and was known as the “Red Priest.” for ten points, name this Baroque composer who depicted Spring in his Four Seasons.",
      "answer": "Antonio Vivaldi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stone slabs were harvested from this body of water by “stonehookers” in Port Credit and other towns. The Scarborough Bluffs lie on the northwest shore of this body of water, whose northeast was connected in 1832 by the Rideau Canal to the Ottawa River. The Niagara River connects this body of water to Lake Erie. Toronto lies on, for ten points, what smallest Great Lake by area, named for a Canadian province?",
      "answer": "Lake Ontario"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2003 example of this action led to the Supreme Court case LULAC v. Perry. Shaw v. Reno banned attempts to do this solely based on race, and it makes use of “packing” and “cracking.” This practice took its name from America’s fifth Vice President, who while as Governor of Massachusetts enacted a district whose elongated shape reminded opponents of a salamander. For ten points, name this practice of drawing electoral districts for partisan advantage.",
      "answer": "gerrymandering"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two men shared this award in 1997 for work on a formula used to calculate values for put and call options. Another winner of this award blamed inefficiencies in distribution for causing world hunger in his Poverty and Famines. In addition to Myron Scholes, Robert Merton, and Amartya Sen, this award has been won by Milton Friedman and 27 other University of Chicago thinkers. In 2008, Paul Krugman won, for ten points, what award, given annually in Sweden for work in a field that studies, among other things, consumption, production, and money?",
        "answer": "Nobel Memorial Prize in Economics or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Science in Memory of Alfred Nobel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Krugman is a columnist and blogger for this newspaper, known as the “Grey Lady.”",
        "answer": "The New York Times"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One ruler of this name brought together the Ten Thousand under Xenophon to fight the broker of the Peace of Antalcidas, Artaxerxes II [art-ah-zerk-zees], his brother. An earlier ruler of this name was killed by the Massagetae [mass-ah-geh-tye] after he refused to marry Queen Tomyris. That ruler of this name disparaged Babylon’s Nabonidus in an inscription on a clay cylinder and was buried in Pasargadae [pass-ar-gah-dye]. For ten points, give this name of a “Great” ruler who founded the Achaemenid Dynasty in Persia.",
        "answer": "Cyrus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Peace of Antalcidas ended a war named for this Greek city-state, which lies on a namesake isthmus roughly halfway between Athens and Sparta.",
        "answer": "Corinth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, the losing side briefly captured Fort Vaux. The winning side in this battle used rapid rotations, cycling in new troops to the front line every two weeks. Erich von Falkenhayn was removed as Chief of Staff after his failure to win this battle, though his goal of “bleeding France white” was met with over 300,000 French casualties. Phillippe P’etain ordered no retreat from, for ten points, what nine-month battle for a fortress complex in World War I?",
        "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Falkenhayn was replaced by a pair of leaders: Erich Ludendorff and this officer, who appointed Hitler Chancellor of Germany in 1933 and is the namesake of a zeppelin that crashed in New Jersey in 1937.",
        "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of this event, its subject wrote that he was “now quite certain that the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away.” During this event, Matthew Ruppert survived being shot in the face during Israel Greene’s attack on the engine house where hostages were being held. Robert E. Lee’s marines ended this event, which sought to capture weapons in preparation for a slave revolt. For ten points, name this October 1859 event in which a federal arsenal was briefly seized by John Brown.",
        "answer": "Raid on Harpers Ferry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brown requested this abolitionist’s help with the raid, but this author of My Bondage and My Freedom and a Narrative of his life as a slave declined.",
        "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hur helped this figure defeat the Amalekites by raising his arms. This man quelled a rebellion by striking a stone on Horeb to create a spring. He ordered the construction of the Tabernacle, and married Zipporah while he was exiled in Midian. He was the brother of Miriam and Aaron, with whom this former prince cast ten plagues on a Pharaoh who may have been Ramses II. The Torah was legendarily written by, for ten points, what Abrahamic religious figure who led the Israelites out of Egypt?",
        "answer": [
          "Moses or Moshe",
          "Musa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was Moses’ spiritual successor. He prayed for the sun to stand still in the sky during a battle with the Amorites.",
        "answer": "Joshua or Jehoshua"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This election year’s Democratic convention was depicted in Norman Mailer’s “Superman Comes to the Supermart.” Claims of election fraud in Texas and Richard Daley’s Chicago led the losing candidate to wait a full day to concede. The first television debate in U.S. history was held during this election; in that debate, the winner of this election was praised for his tan, though radio listeners thought Richard Nixon debated well. For ten points, name this election in which John F. Kennedy became President.",
        "answer": "Election of 1960"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nixon had pledged to perform this action, which may have led to his exhaustion before his first debate. Nixon fulfilled this promise by campaigning in Alaska days before the election was decided.",
        "answer": "visiting all 50 states or similar descriptions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Hodel and Karl Nobiling attempted to assassinate one ruler from this house. Vincent, Count of Benedetti demanded that one prince of this house should reject offers to the Spanish throne, which were sensationalized in the Ems Dispatch. This house was overthrown in the November Revolution, leading to the establishment of the Weimar [VYE-mar] Republic. For ten points, name this German royal house that lost power after the abdication of Wilhelm II.",
        "answer": "House of Hohenzollern"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ems Dispatch triggered this war in 1870. Napoleon III was captured at the Battle of Sedan during this war.",
        "answer": "Franco-Prussian War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One player for this team shared the 1997 MVP award with Brett Favre after rushing for 2,053 yards; that player retired in 1999, even though he was within 1,500 yards of Walter Payton’s career rushing record. In 2010, another player for this team had a touchdown overruled for not maintaining possession for the entire catch under a controversial rule now named for him. For ten points, name this NFL team, whose lack of success under ownership by the Ford family caused Barry Sanders and Calvin Johnson to announce surprisingly early retirements.",
        "answer": [
          "Detroit Lions",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lions have won four NFL championships, though none since their 1957 victory over this team, which didn’t exist from 1996-99 when Art Modell moved the team to Baltimore, where they became the Ravens.",
        "answer": "Cleveland Browns"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Reconstruction",
      "prompt": "In America’s Reconstruction period, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War that it followed.",
          "answer": "American Civil War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, unpopular for his leniency to the South, who was impeached in 1868.",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historian who wrote Black Reconstruction in America and The Souls of Black Folk and debated Booker T. Washington.",
          "answer": "W.E.B. Du Bois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protected the right to vote, regardless of race.",
          "answer": "15th"
        },
        {
          "question": "Perjorative term for Southern whites who supported Reconstruction efforts.",
          "answer": "scalawags"
        },
        {
          "question": "State ruled by the first African-American governor, P. B. S. Pinchback.",
          "answer": "Louisiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two farming needs promised to ex-slaves by the Freedmen’s Bureau.",
          "answer": [
            "forty acres and a mule",
            "in either order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kansas senator featured in Profiles in Courage for voting against the President’s impeachment.",
          "answer": "Edmund Ross"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Renaissance",
      "prompt": "During the Renaissance...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Who diagrammed anatomy in Vitruvian Man and painted the Mona Lisa?",
          "answer": [
            "Leonardo da Vinci",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Who used his telescopes to discover moons of Jupiter, including Io?",
          "answer": [
            "Galileo Galilei",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "What city, the birthplace of that astronomer, built a bell tower on less-than-solid ground?",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who invented a movable-type printing press to enable mass communication?",
          "answer": "Johannes Gutenberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which ruling family of Florence supported the arts and produced four popes?",
          "answer": "Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which “father of empiricism” advanced the scientific method in works like Novum Organum?",
          "answer": "Francis Bacon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Dutch humanist wrote In Praise of Folly?",
          "answer": "Desiderius Erasmus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which English architect designed Banqueting House, Whitehall and Queen’s House, Greenwich?",
          "answer": "Inigo Jones"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reincarnation",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where reincarnation-believing religions like Hinduism and Jainism were founded.",
          "answer": "Republic of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary medieval king who will be reincarnated as England’s savior.",
          "answer": "King Arthur Pendragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mesoamerican people whose soul-preserving mummies were destroyed by Francisco Pizarro.",
          "answer": "Incas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Apple CEO who allegedly believed himself a reincarnated World War II fighter pilot.",
          "answer": "Steve Jobs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former leader of North Korea said to be a reincarnation of his father, Il-Sung.",
          "answer": "Kim Jong-Il"
        },
        {
          "question": "Town in Guyana where 909 Americans died “drinking the Kool-Aid” of a claimed Christ reincarnate.",
          "answer": "Jonestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas city in which David Koresh, another self-proclaimed Christ, was killed in an ATF siege on the Branch Davidian complex.",
          "answer": "Waco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion that describes reincarnation in the Kitab al-Hikma.",
          "answer": "Druze"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Nearly 2,500 of these things were built in Carl Strandlund’s factory in Columbus, Ohio, which was funded by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation; those things, named “Lustron,” were made using enameled-steel that didn’t require (20 pts)",
        "painting. Levitt & Sons built over 17,000 of these things on Long Island, then discriminated against African- Americans by only selling or (10 pts)",
        "renting them to white families. For ten points, name these buildings, whose supply drastically increased after World War II to meet the demand of returning GIs and the Baby Boom."
      ],
      "answer": "houses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed the Belavezha Accords as one of his first acts in office, and he apologized for Korean Airlines Flight 007 after meeting with South Korean President Roh Tae-Woo. Bill Clinton claims that, in 1995, this foreign leader was found on the streets of D.C. calling for pizza while (20 pts)",
        "drunk. A policy of economic “shock therapy,” suggested by Jeffrey Sachs, was implemented by this man in the (10 pts)",
        "1990s. For ten points, name this first President of a post-Cold War Russia, who was responsible for ousting Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author commented on Athenian inheritance laws in one play, in which Hypermnestra is unable to kill her husband after being instructed to do so. This author of the Danaid used Susa as the setting of a play about Xerxes’s defeat at Salamis. He wrote about (20 pts)",
        "Clytemnestra’s killing of her husband and the ensuing revenge of Orestes in a prize-winning trilogy, and two of Oedipus’s sons fight in this author’s (10 pts)",
        "Seven Against Thebes. For ten points, name this ancient Greek tragedian, the author of The Persians and the Oresteia trilogy."
      ],
      "answer": "Aeschylus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Vaughn Meader popularized this action, using phrases like “move ahead with great vigah,” while Chevy Chase performed this action with bumbling slapstick. The word “strategery” [stra-TEE-jer-ee] was coined for use in one of these actions by (20 pts)",
        "Will Ferrell, who staged a one-man play, You’re Welcome, America, featuring this action. Luther, the “Anger Translator,” used a megaphone to proclaim “I am not a (10 pts)",
        "Muslim!” to complement Jordan Peele’s performance of this action. For ten points, name this genre of comedy, currently performed on Saturday Night Live by Jay Pharoah as Barack Obama."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "comedic impersonations of the U.S. President",
        "descriptions of comedic sketches featuring an actor playing the President"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an effort to gain reconnaissance about this man’s army, Jeb Stuart and over 1,000 cavalrymen rode completely around it. This man’s forces retreated to Malvern Hill at the end of the Seven Days Battles, bringing this man’s (20 pts)",
        "Peninsular Campaign to a disappointing end. His failure to pursue the outnumbered Confederate army at Antietam led President Lincoln to (10 pts)",
        "promote Ambrose Burnside. For ten points, name this man who faced Lincoln in the 1864 Presidential election after being replaced as Commander of the Army of the Potomac in 1862."
      ],
      "answer": "George B. McClellan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Giulio Clovio landed this artist a job in Rome in the Palazzo Farnese, but he was later dismissed for being against the teachings of Michelangelo. His works were judged to not completely follow the rules of the Counter-Reformation, preventing him from working for (20 pts)",
        "Philip II. One of his works contrasts a dark and stormy sky with green hills and a cathedral spire, and in another, the (10 pts)",
        "clouds part to receive Don Gonzalo Ruiz. For ten points, name this Mannerist artist of Burial of the Count of Orgaz and View of Toledo, a Spanish artist from Crete."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "El Greco",
        "Dom´enikos Theotok´opoulos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Pope Leo X owned one of these animals named Hanno, and a trader named Isaac helped procure one of these animals, named Abdul Abbas, for (20 pts)",
        "Charlemagne. A marriage deal with Chandragupta Maurya gave the Seleucid Empire 500 of these animals, which served at the (10 pts)",
        "Battle of Ipsus. Spear lines were largely ineffective against the charge of these animals, due to their size. For ten points, name these pachyderms who also crossed the Alps with Hannibal."
      ],
      "answer": "elephants"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Vel’ d’Hiv [vell deev] Roundup in this city collected much of its Jewish population, and Marcel Petiot became notorious for strangling Jewish victims in this city during World War II. Only men were executed for treason by this city at Fort (20 pts)",
        "Mont-Valerien. Albert Speer and Arno Breker toured this city with Hitler, who ordered General von Choltitz to burn it down after it was recovered by (10 pts)",
        "de Gaulle’s Free French forces in 1944. For ten points, name this city where Hitler took a famous picture in front of the Eiffel Tower."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    }
  ]
}